<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Liquor alchahest, or, A discourse of that immortal dissolvent of Paracelsus &amp; Helmont it being one of those two wonders of art and nature, which radically dissolves all animals, vegitables, and minerals into their principles, without being in the least alter'd, either in weight or activity, after a thousand dissolutions, &amp;c. / Published by J.A. pyrophilus.</title>
            <author>Starkey, George, 1627-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15014</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11924061</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11924061</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 515:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Liquor alchahest, or, A discourse of that immortal dissolvent of Paracelsus &amp; Helmont it being one of those two wonders of art and nature, which radically dissolves all animals, vegitables, and minerals into their principles, without being in the least alter'd, either in weight or activity, after a thousand dissolutions, &amp;c. / Published by J.A. pyrophilus.</title>
                  <author>Starkey, George, 1627-1665.</author>
                  <author>J. A., Pyrophilus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 55 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. &amp; N.T. for W. Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to George Starkey.  Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 55.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Glasgow University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alchemy --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50996:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50996:1"/>
            <p>Liquor Alchaheſt, OR A DISCOURSE <hi>Of that Immortal Diſſolvent</hi> OF <hi>Paracelſus</hi> &amp; <hi>Helmont.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It being one of thoſe two Wonders of <hi>ART</hi> and <hi>NATURE,</hi> which radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally diſſolves all Animals, Vegitables and Minerals into their principles, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being in the leaſt alter'd, either in weight or activity, after a Thouſand Diſſolutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>J.A. PYROPHIL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ergo Medicinae operam datis ſummo ſtudio id adniti debetis ut Alchaeſt prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parare diſcatis propter averſionem multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum morborum qui ab Haepate oriuntur <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Paracelſ. Archidox lib. de viribus mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brorum cap. 6. de viribus Hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atis.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> &amp; <hi>N. T.</hi> for <hi>W. Cademan</hi> at the <hi>Popes-Head</hi> in the Lower Walk of the <hi>New-Exchange,</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50996:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50996:2"/>
            <head>To the truly Honourable <hi>ROBERT BOYLE,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT I have made choice of your Honour to Patronize this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthume Tract, will appear no wonder to ſuch that have
<pb facs="tcp:50996:3"/>been acquainted with your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in this more occult Philoſophy of the Adeptiſts, as well as with your Candour to encourage ſuch who have been but pretenders to Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotechny. I know
<pb facs="tcp:50996:3"/>well, you affect not Flattery; and for me to ſpeak much, would but leſſen, the World having been (by ſo many) acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with your worth. All the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe I make your Honour is, That
<pb facs="tcp:50996:4"/>the preſent Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe is yours by Right, the Author having in his Pyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techny Aſſerted, begun this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſo that I only ſurrender what's your own. If the Nobleneſs of the Subject be
<pb facs="tcp:50996:4"/>not ſufficient to plead my excuſe for this Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I hope your wonted Charity to forgive others, will not be ſtraitned to me, ſince I had no other Ambition in the Publication thereof, then the
<pb facs="tcp:50996:5"/>promoting the publick good, by inſpiriting others to do the like, and giving this further teſtimony of my ſelf, that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours Obliged Humble Servant <hi>J. ASTELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>From the <hi>Golden Globe</hi> againſt <hi>Strand-Bridge.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:50996:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>AFter a long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate with my ſelf, I found I was obliged to put forth this little Tractate, not only to ſhow my juſtneſs to the Dead, but my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of gratifying the living; for in an Age
<pb facs="tcp:50996:6"/>wherein this kind of Philoſophy receives ſuch great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (having acquired many eminent Practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as well as Patrons) and by the happy diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of diligent ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, hath made ſo large an improvement: I thought I could do no leſs then communicate this Eſſay concerning the Immortal Liquor Alcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hest, that being the great
<pb facs="tcp:50996:6"/>Key which unlocks Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures choiceſt Secrets; and which at preſent is ſo diligently ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The Author of it was a perſon ſo indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly laborious in the ſearching after natures choiceſt myſteries, that he ſpared not for pains nor costs in the hunting after the true knowledge of the most abſtruce Philoſophy. That his acquirements
<pb facs="tcp:50996:7"/>were great, is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the World, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to thoſe who had any intimate familiarity with him, his Writings teſtifie his ability in the Philoſophy, or learning of the Schools, as well as in that of Nature, his diſcoveries having truly intituled him <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophus per Ignem.</hi> It was his misfortune to juſtifie Truth in an Age when Chymiſtry had few
<pb facs="tcp:50996:7"/>Friends that durſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to juſtifie her, yet ſo great an effect had his Writings, back'd with Truth, that the Eyes of many were opened, and occaſioned ſeveral to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Proſelytes to Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotechny. It would not, I believe, leſſen the eſteem of ſome eminent Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, ſhould they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with me, that they had from him thoſe true fundamentals of Art
<pb facs="tcp:50996:8"/>that hath rendred them thus famous. So that this preſent Age reaps the benefit of his more early Studies. Had he not met with many Croſſes and Troubles, doubtleſs his diſcoveries had been greater; and had not he been cut off by that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Peſtilence, 1666. When he was juſt riſing out of thoſe Clouds which Eclipſed his worth, it would quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:50996:8"/>have appeared to the World, notwithſtanding the malice of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, That he was a true follower of Nature. Pyrotechny hath not had a bolder Champion; and I verily believe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Enemies will now confeſs, they are convinced of the ineffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of Vulgar Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments; and that there is an abſolute neceſſity for a new method of
<pb facs="tcp:50996:9"/>Phyſick, as to the Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malentick part: for dayly ſuch incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are made upon this noble faculty, that if not ſpeedily prevented, it will be of little or no eſteem. The Common method of Phyſick being paſſed into the hands of all kind of unletter'd People; and the chief remedy that is left, would be a diligent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after noble Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,
<pb facs="tcp:50996:9"/>ſuch that are agreeable to Nature, which the Author of this Tract candidly did not only hint at, but diſcover as plainly as it was fit, without incurring the ſame inconveniencies as did attend the making publick the Common me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Phyſicks which faults are not only to be taken notice of on the Gallenical part, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thoſe abuſes are to
<pb facs="tcp:50996:10"/>be conſider'd which have ſprung from Chymistry. It being common in this latter Age, for many to cry up themſelves for great Chymiſts, who (ignorantly decrying all others) have hardly known well the Names, (much leſs the uſes of Chymical Veſſels) theſe Men have had the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence to impoſe on the World Trifles, for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Remedies; many
<pb facs="tcp:50996:10"/>of which undiſcreetly adminiſtred, have truly cured all Diſeaſes; by giving the unwary Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients their Paſports in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another World. But I ſhall paſs them over, as being unworthy my time to particularize their Cheats, which I have not patience to think of, nor can any true Son of Art conſider without reſentment, the abuſes that are daily
<pb facs="tcp:50996:11"/>committed by this Farra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go of Impoſtors, that have been, and will ever be, a diſhonour to the honeſt Profeſſors of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotechny. The only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient in this Caſe, wherein the good of Mankind is concerned, the Lives of Perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more to be valued, then all other worldly conſideraoions, is this; for ſome well experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Artists, to put to
<pb facs="tcp:50996:11"/>ſale to the World, ſuch true Remedies, with their uſes, as may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificial for the eradica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Diſeaſes, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines that have been known to be ſucceſsful by reiterated experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not thoſe duely made, not conjectural. By this means the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of that moſt noble faculty of Phyſick will be recover'd and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and the truth of
<pb facs="tcp:50996:12"/>Chymical Remedies will be manifested, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the reproaches of malicious gain-ſayers. This the noble <hi>Helmont</hi> did; and by this way will it ſoon appear, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no thoſe refined Chymical Medicaments, are not more ſafe, more eaſie, and more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al for eradicating of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, then the Common <hi>Gallenical apparatus</hi> of Medicine. But ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:50996:12"/>Artiſts, whoever they be that will thus expoſe any thing for the good of Mankind, I am ſure will be more ingenious then thoſe undiſcreet pretenders to Chymiſtry, as to make the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality of healing Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, can any way be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from any one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Medicine; it being impoſſible, were they Maſters of the
<pb facs="tcp:50996:13"/>
               <hi>Grand Elixar,</hi> with that to cure all Diſeaſes. I come now to ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Tract, who was Dr. <hi>George Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key,</hi> (my very good Friend) a Man whoſe Writings ſpoke him more to the World then his Perſon or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe;<note place="margin">Natures Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, &amp; <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monts</hi> Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Pyrotech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> Aſſerted.</note> whoſe moral fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings I dare no more justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, but he was a Man,
<pb facs="tcp:50996:13"/>and as ſuch, the beſt of us are ſubject to erre, which conſideration ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our Charity to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. When imployed in Pyrotechnies School, Nature had not a more diligent Scholler; and who, to my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (not in vain) wrought for many years upon this Subject he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, I never could get a ſight of the
<pb facs="tcp:50996:14"/>Alchaheſt perfected by him, whether occaſioned by the importunities of Patients for Remedies, whoſe condition would not admit the tarrying for Medicines of ſo high a preparation, or his want of conveniencies, being hurried from place to place, I know not, yet have I ſeen and known him, poſſeſſor of ſeveral Magiſteries, and not many Months before his
<pb facs="tcp:50996:14"/>death, I knew him Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of a mercurial Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, whoſe effects were ſuch, That it merited the name of an <hi>Arcanum.</hi> Had he lived, I know not what greater proofs he might have given of the certainty of ſuch an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Solvent. His Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments deduced from thoſe hints the moſt noble <hi>Helmont</hi> gives are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, if duely weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the true ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb facs="tcp:50996:15"/>after Truth may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no ſmall Light from him; for my own part, I have no reaſon to repent my Labours, and time ſpent in this Study, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being very Grateful to her diligent followers. From this Fountain have I gain'd a Salt, which diſſolved in Rain Water, <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:arsenic2"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>arsenic</ex>
               </expan> being amalgam'd with another Metal, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſed to boil in a Sand Furnace for the
<pb facs="tcp:50996:15"/>ſpace of two hours the Amalgame was diſſolved into a Liquor, with as much eaſe as Sugar diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves in Water. This I did in the preſence of two Friends, no mean Artiſts. Therefore not to be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon, with which Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, my <hi>Menſtruum</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeparated from it, and further operated on, I cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red deploracle Poxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall forbear to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe any further, what
<pb facs="tcp:50996:16"/>other medioaments I have made by the help of good Diſſolvents, reſolving, if God ſpare me life, to put forth <hi>Pyrotechny Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant,</hi> which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, had he lived, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to do, which will be an Explanation of his Pyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techny Aſſerted, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Hiſtory of Nature, comprehended in thoſe Subjects.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50996:16"/>
            <head>Liquor Alchahest, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> am come now to the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the great Circulate, or immortal di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvent of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus,</hi> and <hi>Helmont,</hi> not lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here the foundation of its Uſe and Excellency, which I preſume is ſufficiently believ'd in the World already, who had rather now hear tidings how it may be attain'd, then be tantaliz'd with a large En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comium
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50996:17"/>of its worth and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue. I elſewhere taught its Nature, Nativity and Efficacy, although briefly I ſhall here come to a more large handling of it, yet with caution as well as candor. It is (as I ſaid) a Spiritual Salt, or Saline Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which by reaſon of its tranſcendent purity, cannot be corruptively diſſipated, and not finding any body ſo noble (at leaſt more noble) then it ſelf; diſdains to be wedded unto any, nor is it capable of a diverſe ferment from it ſelf, and ſo not liable to tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: the knowledge and preparation of it, is the work
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50996:17"/>of moſt abſtruce Philoſophy, the hope and crown of the <hi>adepti.</hi> O immortal Ens or Liquour! which penetrates all bodies, and perfectly reduces them to their firſt Ens or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, without any loſs of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or pondus, but remains in number, weight, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the ſame after a 1000 times acting upon bodily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes; only one conquers and ſubjugates it, and is in it ſelf deſtroyed in its deſtruction. It is vile and yet precious, it coſts nothing, every man hath it, the poor as well as the rich; <hi>Adam</hi> carryed it with him out of Paradice, it is moſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50996:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſecret in <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in the <hi>Macrocoſme;</hi> it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys and conquers all bodies, and ſubjugates the moſt rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious nature. 'Tis the product of Urine, then which nothing more common to come by, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more difficult to work on, well therefore ſaid <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> that its preparation was moſt tedious: And moſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrote he of ſuch as contemn ſo vile and ſordid a thing, and diſdain to learn by the fire what its contents are, <hi>That true Wiſdom doth and will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe them.</hi> For the plainer unfolding the myſtery of its nativity and preparation, I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50996:18"/>ſhall recite my own broileries, how I hunted after it, and how after many years ſearch, and and infinite errors, I at length attained it, if there be any thing deſerving imitation in my example, follow it, and perhaps (God bleſſing your ſtudies, labours &amp; watchings) you may at laſt attain your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, as I, through the undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved mercy of God, at laſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mine. I had not been long converſant in the writings of that noble Phyloſopher; but I ſoon (from ſome of his expreſſions) gathered a ſtrong preſumption, that Urine was the ſubject. Eſpecially from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50996:19"/>that place in his <hi>Trac. de Lith.</hi> where he thus ſpeaks, <hi>Eſt in Natura univerſi,</hi> &amp;c. There is in the whole nature of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, but only one fire, (which is our conſuming <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi>) and ſo likewiſe there is but one only Liquor which is of power to diſſolve all ſolid bodies into their firſt matter, without being its ſelf in the leaſt changed or weakned in its virtue; which thoſe that are adept know and can teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie. But in the activity of other Spirits, the diſſolvable bodies can never radically mix themſelves with the diſſolving Liquor; and therefore, though
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50996:19"/>they are corroded, yet is not this to be eſteemed an intire diſſolution, for every acid Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (being corroſive) by corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding another body, is coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and in a manner fixt, and becomes tranſmuted into the form of a condenſed Salt, not that the body, which (without alteration) endured what the pontick Spirit could work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, acts any thing towards its coagulation, but it ſelf by its proper corroſive activity, is Coagulated of its own accord. Thus far <hi>Helmont</hi> in that place, who elſewhere ſpeaking of his examination of all Salts, by way of Analyzing them, found
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50996:20"/>by all trials poſſible, that their Spirits were ſtill acid, except only Alcalizate Salts, and thoſe of the Eſſential Sulphurs of vegetals. The Spirit of Mans Urine, notwithſtanding, was neither Acid nor Alcali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zate, but meerly Saline, alſo the Spirit of the Urine of Beaſts. Hence I conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that in one of theſe two the Immortal Liquor muſt find its primitive original, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on good reaſon, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all acid Spirits; (and by conſequence the Spirits of all other Salts in the World) Nor was the controverſie long deciding between Alcalizate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50996:20"/>and Urinous Salts, conſidering the words of <hi>Helmont:</hi> when (ſaith he) I diſtinguiſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ☿ies, and the Salts and 🜍s of <hi>Concretes,</hi> by an analytical reſolution of them, I wondred at the ſluggiſh, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active nature of the ☿ial com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the dignity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent activity of the other two principles (to wit Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous and Saline) More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over I found, ſaith he, thoſe Salts more dull and languid, which partaked of the nature of 🜍, but of Acalizate Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and thoſe of Eſſential vegitable Sulphurs, he ſaith definitively, that their ſaline
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50996:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>Acrimony is fat and Sulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erous, nor eaſily or ſpeedily reducible into Salt, unleſs by a tedious inverſion of their whole ſubſtance; whence I obſerved, that Alcalyes were not to be volatized (duely and truly) but by means of eſſential vegetable Oyls or 🜍s. Secondly, That being vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, they retained their Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureous fatneſs a long time, till by a tedious inverſion of the whole ſubſtance, the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureous nature was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Saline. Thirdly, Yet (even then) thoſe ſaline Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calizate ſpirits could not give the immortal Liquor, becauſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50996:21"/>Meretriciouſly addicted to wed any ſubject, and by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution thereof, to be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into a Coagulative vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Salt, as <hi>Helmont</hi> expreſly teacheth in his <hi>Tract. de Feb.</hi> as alſo in his <hi>Tract. de poteſt Medicam,</hi> his words are theſe, <hi>If,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>you cannot attain to the</hi> Arcanum <hi>of our Fire, learn</hi> (<hi>as a</hi> ſuccedaneum <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>) <hi>to make Alcalyes volatile, and with their Spirits perform your diſſolutions; which, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they leave their diſsol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Bodies (when digeſted in our Stomacks) yet have they by their Diſſolution of, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulation upon them, borrowed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50996:22"/>ſo much of their virtue, as by it to be able to overcome most Diſeaſes.</hi> And in another place he ſaith, <hi>If Spirit of Salt of</hi> Tartar <hi>diſſolve Quick-Silver, Silver, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicornes Horn, Crabs Eyes, or any other ſimple; it will cure (not only all Feavours) but most Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes indifferently.</hi> And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making diſtinction; not that I expect the Quick-ſilver, Silver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould paſs with the Spirit into the Veins; but it is ſufficient that the Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizate Spirit is by means of theſe Bodies, reduced into the nature of a Volatile and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulable Salt; and in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50996:22"/>Stomack being firſt digeſted, (as other Meats are) it it paſſeth into the Meſeraicks, being carried thither by the Urine; and in its paſſage re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth and looſneth whatever obſtructing filth it meets with, by virtue of its Exotick qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, borrowed in diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the bodies whereon it was coagulated. And in his <hi>Tract. de poteſt Med.</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Alcalyes, I perceived or felt (ſaith he) that they are utterly void of all ſeminal power, or properties, and have only a Saponary, Abſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and reſolving nature, wherewith they are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50996:23"/>except they be made volatile, and then I was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that they re-aſſumed Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamick ſeminal Vertues, and the radical principles of theſe concretes (by whoſe volatile 🜍s they were revived and made volatile.) But adds, <q>I was ſenſible how eaſily theſe volatile Alcalyes are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muted into new and various forms, ſince they unite moſt readily to any Bodyes, and wed therewith: acting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the native diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Bodyes, to which they are thus conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively aſſociated.</q> By theſe teſtimonyes of this noble and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50996:23"/>moſt acute Phyloſopher, whom I felt underſtandingly, having firſt often read him, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider'd his words, I was wholly confirmed in my opinion concerning Urine, as the only ſubject in which this ſecret Liquor was to be ſought and attained. Which opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mine was dayly more and more ſtrengthned by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral expreſſions of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this ſubject, one of which I recited before, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That Wiſdom did (and for ever will) deſpiſe all ſuch who think ſcorn to learn by the fire what the contents, nature, and properties of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50996:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Urine are, how ſordid and contemptible a thing ſoever it ſeem and appear to be. Therefore in his Tract. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſix digeſtions in man, he uſeth this expreſſion concerning the Salt of Mans Urine, that in the whole ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteme of the Univerſe it had not its fellow or peere. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sea nor Fountain Salt, Salt <hi>Peter</hi> or <hi>Gemme;</hi> In a word, not any natural Salt whatſoever, nor yet the Salt of the Urine of Beaſts, was comparable to it. The ſame he affirms in his <hi>Tract de Lith.</hi> And inſtances in the Urine of a Horſe, which he found far
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50996:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>to fall ſhort of the dignity of Mans Urine, not having in it, or by any preparation, yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that noble Spirit, which in Mans Urine was to be found, which Coagulated Spirit of Urine in an inſtant, not into a fixed body, but an Aetherical ſubtle, ſpiritual Salt, then which nature hath not a more ſpiritual penetrative Creature; of the Salt of Urine he before ſaid, That he knew not if or no the whole World afforded any thing of a more ſubtle nature: comparing which with that Paragraph concerning the Immortal diſſolvent in his <hi>Tract. de Medicam poteſt:</hi> he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50996:25"/>calls it the higheſt and moſt noble of Salts, which hath attained its utmoſt pitch in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſubtilty and purity, penetrating all things, and is the only agent in the World, which acting upon Bodyes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains always immutable, and with eaſe reſolves all things, and brings them into ready obedience, liquefying and (at the ſame time) volatizing them, as Snow is melted in warm water. I obſerved, I ſay, in the works of this Philoſopher, the Liquor Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaheſt, and the Circulated Salt of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> otherwiſe called the greater Circulate,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50996:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>were Synonimous, and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently uſed to ſignifie this fire of Hell, or immutable diſſolvent; and where is it to be found but in that ſubject whoſe Spirit is even ſaline, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Acid or Alcalizate? Not without cauſe therefore (by way of incouragement) he thus allureth the ſtudious ſearchers of truth; ſeek (my Brethren) and as many of you as are ſedulous and diligent ſhall find truth ready to meet you with open arms, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace you, and crown your ſearches with unſpeakable joy. Firſt learn to diſſolve the Due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech, or Stone of the Bladder
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50996:26"/>or Reins, or the Gravel of either, in a Glaſs with a Tepid Liquor, inoffenſive to either Stomack or Bladder, rejoyce, for you are near the great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, then learn to diſſolve the Ludus, and reduce it into a volatile Salt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now this Spirit or Liquor which will thus reſolve the Duelech, is the ſecond, which is drawn from Urine (putrified by long di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion.) The former Coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating Spirit (of <hi>Aquae Vitae</hi> rectified) being ſome dayes before taken away by diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. From the teſtimonyes of this moſt acute and truly adept Philoſopher by the fire,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50996:26"/>I ſet my mind to conſider the thing it ſelf, and found it a ſubject of great wonder. My Experience convinced me, that it was an <hi>Anomalous Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulum,</hi> which being it ſelf a moſt ſubtile Spirit, was yet the Coagulation of other (and none but) Spirits, and thoſe only vinous, for although it ſeems to Coagulate, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys utterly all acid Spirits, and returns them into Water inſipid, or rather the acid Spirit, attempting by its Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſiveneſs, to deſtroy this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Spirit, which is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely volatile and flying: It the better to defend it ſelf,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50996:27"/>aſſumes the form of a coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Body (as Water to withſtand the active force of the Cold which would turn it into a Gas, cruſts it ſelf by its own action, into an Ice) And ſo this moſt fugacious penetrative Spirit, plays un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Maske of a far more fixed (yet totally volatile) Body of Salarmoniack, while the Spirit (to avoid whoſe tyranny it thus diſguiſed it ſelf) is by its own fretting activity totally deſtroyed from what it was, and becomes a mere elemental Water: That this Coagulation, and diſguiſed fixation, with a total ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50996:27"/>of the acute Urinary odour and taſt, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from it ſelf, and not the acid Spirit (effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively.) I demonſtrate, firſt in that upon any Acidity, fixt or volatile, it will do the ſame thing, and become the ſame Salt, and ſo the acid Calci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of Vitriol, as well as its acid volatile Spirit will cauſe the ſame ſaline product. But Secondly, were the Urinous Spirit coagulated paſſively, it would be really and actually tranſmuted, and become ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, whereas the ſame Urinous Spirit (identically and numerically) is (in this action) but veiled under a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50996:28"/>Larva, or masked under the diſguiſe of a more fixed body (as Water ſtill remaining the ſame, counterfeits a body of appearing Glaſs, being indeed but the ſame water identically, in the diſguiſe of Ice.) And this the affuſion of a <hi>Lixivium</hi> of Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> or any other Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caly, will eaſily diſcover, when in the twinkling of an eye, or the ſpace of the ſame quickeſt thought, the ſame Spirit of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, in the ſame <hi>pondus</hi> &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and with the ſame formal properties, will diſtill over as before, re-aſſuming the ſame ſubtlety of odour, fieryneſs of taſt, being equally Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50996:28"/>coagulating alſo Spirit of Wine, ſpeedily, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and ſolemnly, as if it had never been coagulated. Whereas the acid Spirit is turned into an inſipid Water; having ſpent it ſelf in vain upon this diſguiſed Body of <hi>Sal Armoniack.</hi> And Thirdly, were the coagulation and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mifixation actively from the Corroſive Spirit, which is moſt fiery, and in its tumultuous action, cauſeth a ſenſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable heat to the touch, it could not upon a Spirit moſt exquiſitely hot and fiery, actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally imprint that <hi>Lunar Blas,</hi> which is apparent in <hi>Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack:</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:50996:29"/>For it being in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and quality hot, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially and really (although hiddenly) containing the moſt fiery Spirit of Urine, of which a drop in an inſtant will veſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Toung or Lips, as powerfully and ſpeedily as the moſt fiery potential cautery; and the Spirit by its moſt acute ſharp odour (arguing the moſt exquiſite heat of it when rectified) being ſo volatile and penetrative, ſcarce any ſtopple can keep it confin'd to the Veſſel which contains it; and ſo piercingly acute, that no humane, or other Animals Organs of ſmelling can long
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50996:29"/>endure its odour, without a threatned Syncope, if not an Apoplexie for the time doth yet ſo powerfully operate by a <hi>Lunar Blas,</hi> that if <hi>Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack</hi> be put in an Urinal, or other thick Glaſs, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter poured on it, ſtraightway it cauſeth ſuch an extremity of Cold, as will actually freeze Water on the outſide of the Urinal, yea although <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:antimony"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>antimony</ex>
               </expan>, or 🜍, or ☿, be ſublimed with it, which are of a hot fiery Nature; And this <hi>Lunar Blas</hi> is inſperable from it as long as it appears in the form of a more fixed Body of Salt, where obſerve by the by, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50996:30"/>Cold is a real poſitive Ens or Being, and not a bare priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of heat, as the Schools moſt coldly teach. (It is I ſay) a Being which in the twinkling of an eye, can by the irradiating Blas of moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Sal Armoniack</hi> be ſent through the impervious ſides of a ſtrong Glaſs, ſo as in an inſtant to produce Cold in its glaciating extream, which was not ſo the moment before. Therefore Secondly, this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be an impreſſion ſtampt upon the moſt fiery Corroſive; but is done by the activity of the Urinous Spirit upon it ſelf, which it is ſo ſollicited too by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50996:30"/>the excitation of the Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Spirit, as Water actually cruſt it ſelf with Ice, by the Irritation of extream Cold, which otherwiſe threatens ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine to its preſent form of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence. And Thirdly, By a peculiar priviledge the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator hath given this Spirit, the moſt Cold <hi>Lunar Blas,</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries it ſelf to this (naturally hot in quality) ſubject, which it influentially imprints on whatſoever it toucheth; ſo ſoon as moiſture (over which the cold Moon by its Light is preſident) is poured on its Body; that the Atomes of Water and Salt do embrace
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50996:31"/>each other. Fourthly, no marvell, ſince the Lunar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence (having dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver moiſture) is the main in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of reducing things to their firſt matter (as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in Inke, Broth, Jellies, Fleſh, or Fiſh, once throughly Frozen) that the acid Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive Spirits, (which acting their fury upon Bodies, are variouſly coagulated into fixt coagulated Salts, of times very Corroſive) are in this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by a retrograde reduction, brought into mere inſipid Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Water: For let the Corroſive Spirit be of what kind ſoever, Acetous, Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50996:31"/>Nitrous of Salt Gemme, Sea Salt, or any other acidity, the product of <hi>Sal Armoniack</hi> is ſtill the ſame, as alſo the <hi>Lunar Blas</hi> inhering in it, if not appearing with the ſame countenance at firſt coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet by ſublimation of the coagulated Salt, the iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity is ſoon perceptible; and the ſame reduction of the Corroſive Spirit to inſipid Water, is as well the end of one acidity as another; By which the action of the Spirit upon it ſelf, (not ſuffering a paſſive coagulation from the acid Corroſive) is beyond diſpute, and out of queſtion.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:50996:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>So then this is the original and production of <hi>Sal Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack</hi> the moſt ſubtle acute pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrative Urinous Spirit, meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with an acid Corroſive; this ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eks (by a furious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, to deſtroy that; which to prevent, the Urinous Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, counterfeits a Body by a <hi>ſpontaneus</hi> Coagulation, which (as more permanent) it op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to the fury of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive ſpiritual Acidity. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Body the <hi>Lunar Blas</hi> concenteates, and joins it ſelf, dwelling in it inviſibly, yet acting viſibly.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:50996:32"/>
            <p>The acid Spirit, fretting it ſelf in vain upon this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful body, receiving a deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination from its Cold <hi>Lunar Blas,</hi> ends in the total extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of its ſaline ſeminal vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and that which in other actings, receives from various bodies, various coagulations, into divers forms of Salts fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from this counterfeit body (guarded by a <hi>Lunar Blas</hi> (or influence) receives its final deſtruction, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>comes inſipid) Elemental water; thus that the Spirit through itr own activity is exantlated (by a fruſtaneous acting on this larvated body) is from
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50996:33"/>it ſelf; But that the end of this fury, and excandeſcence, ſhould be the total extinction of its ſaline life, or being, is wholly to be attributed to the <hi>Lunar Blas,</hi> which is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately and inſeparately wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the form of Sal Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack; whoſe coagulation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that diſguiſe of a body, is by its own action, on it ſelf, according to an unerring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct by which the wiſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hath injoyn'd it to act.</p>
            <p>This I have deſcribed the more at large, that the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious might lay this true rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this anomalous Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as a ſure foundation to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50996:33"/>work upon in the moſt ſeeret diſcovery of what only a true mental man will intellectually apprehend, and intuitively behold, with the clear ſight of the Soul or mind. For as there is a <hi>Sal Armoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack</hi> Vulgar, which ſcarce any Fool but knows; ſo is there alſo a <hi>Sal Armoniack</hi> of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, which only true elect Sons of Learning know: In the circulation of which, is the perfection of the hope of all true adept Brothers of Art, ſo far as concerns this ſire of Hell, which is Fire and yet Water, Water, and yet no Water, Air, and yet
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50996:34"/>condenſible, not Corroſive, yet the moſt ſharp and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Corroſive: A choice Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, cleanſing and purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nature, yet the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and conquerour of Bodies. But vinous Spirits are actually and actively coagulated by Spirit of Urine, and it ſelf is actually con-coagulated with them, of which coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation <hi>Helmont</hi> gives not an unlike <hi>Elogium,</hi> to that of the Immortal Liquor it ſelf; namely, That it is not made by a bare aſſociation of parts, but a marrying of each to other in the bond of indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveable unity, a production
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50996:34"/>of a new Ens, which is a neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral, moſt ſubtle, ſpiritual body, diſtinct from either parent. Here is a ſpiritual body ariſing from two, yet without any diverſity of fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for a vinous Spirit is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, and centrally one with the Spirit of Mans Urine, by virtue and efficacy of which, it coagulates Spirit of Wine, and is coagulated it ſelf, which cannot happen to any Urinous Spirit, unleſs by the influential power of a vinous; which is the only coagulable object (primarily) of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Urine. With which, if it meet with any other vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50996:35"/>Spirit, eſſentially united, it coagulates it ſelf therewith, ſo the Oils of Spices, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doriferous Vegetables, being firſt intimately aſſociated to a Urinous Spirit, are with it coagulated together into one ſpiritual body by rectifi'd Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Urine; and truly, upon ſerious conſideration, the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſallity of the nature and energy of Urine in its Spirit, cannot ſufficiently be admir'd. For (mediately at the leaſt) there is nothing in the whole univerſe (except the central heart of ☿, and one thing which alone is its compere, the one deſtroying it, the other
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50996:35"/>untoucht by its activity) which is not either by it tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muted into its own nature, or elſe abſolutely deſtroy'd, and reduced into clear and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental water.</p>
            <p>For demonſtrating this, it will not be amiſs to take an exact ſurvey, at leaſt briefly of all ſublimary Concrete Bodyes. In the Mineral King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the central heart of ☿, (as was aboveſaid) excepted, all Sulphurs, mettaline and mineral, yea even of ☉, <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, and ☿ themſelves, are by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterate cohobations, turned into ſaline Liquors, or Spirits, and they at laſt return to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipid
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50996:36"/>elemental Water; ſo all Stones not calcinable by this ſire of Hell, are made into Salts, which by oft circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or cohobating with this Liquor, are volatiz'd, and by addition return a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laſt into Water. All calcinable ſtones and ſhells, yield an Alcaly, which being by eſſential Oyls volatized, unite with rectifi'd Spirit of Wine, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coagulated by an Urinous Spirit; which ſubtle Coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, being by a convenient acidity made into a more abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding bodily Salt, and ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, whatever will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally abide therewith, is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50996:36"/>ſtraightway in form of an <hi>Heterogeneous</hi> Liquor, and by an eaſie art is robb'd of its ſeminal Craſis, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to inſipid water. All Animals, their Fleſh, Bloud, and Bones, beſides a Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Liquor (which is ſoon turn'd to elementary water) give a fat Sulphur, and an urinary Salt, if not by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate diſtillation, yet by a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious maceration by ferment and putrifaction. The <hi>Caput Mort</hi> becomes by the cohoba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Circulated Salt, a mere Salt, and at laſt becomes Water, as all Earths, Stones, or the like, the Urinary Salts
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50996:37"/>being purified by rectification, and ſemifixed into a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent body by proper Aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, become a <hi>Sal Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack;</hi> which in ſublimation (loſing its Heterogeneityes) ariſes univocally the ſame with other of the ſame kind. The fat by diſtillation is volatized, and by an Alcaly becomes ſuſceptible of union with Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of con-coagulation by an Urinous Spirit, and by aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dityes proper is made a <hi>Sal Armoniack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Urine of all Creatures giving a Spirit, is by an aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity made a tractable body
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50996:37"/>of Salt, and by ſubliming with other <hi>Sal Armoniack;</hi> what is not made one identi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally therewith, is ſeparated as Heterogeneus, and by an eaſie art totally deſtroyed. All horns and hoofs, either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, or being before buried, yield an Oyle, and an Urinous Salt; and may be handled, as I ſaid before, in the like caſe, of the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts of Fleſh, Bloud, and Bones. All Trees by burning, give a fixt Alcalid Mercurial Liquor, a volatile Sulphur, and a volatile Salt in the ſoot, which is plainly and truly Urinous; ſome Spices, Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50996:38"/>Seeds, Barks and Roots of Trees, give an Eſſential Oyle, others expreſt Oyle: at leaſt, all expreſt Oyles by reiterate diſtillations, being rectifi'd and cohobated with Alcalyes, become capable of union with Spirit of Wine, and conſequently of coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by, and ſubjugation too, Urinous Spirits; which with whatever will not hold coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and ſublimation, is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated as Heterogeneall, and eaſily reducible to inſipid Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The deſtruction of all acid Spirits (by urinous) I taught before. In a word, whatever in the World is (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50996:38"/>the cential Nut of <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:arsenic2"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>arsenic</ex>
               </expan>) is either fixt or volatile, the fixt, either ſaline or not, what is not ſaline, by art is made ſo, and both (by art and pains) become volatile; and being volatized, are ſoon reduced to Elemental Water, robb'd of all ſeminal virtue; fixt Alcalyes are volatized, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed with vinous Spirits; and coagulable (together with them) by means of Urinous: Oyles become Salts Volatile, and ſo commiſcible with Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Wine, and ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable by Urinous: Vinous Spirits are moſt univerſal, all Herbs, Roots, Barks, Fruits,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50996:39"/>Honey, Suggar, Leaves, Grain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, Flowers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yielding (by fermentation) a true vinous Spirit, which (by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterate rectifications) looſing the qualities of the <hi>(media vita)</hi> of its concrete, is not diſcernable from others, and is <hi>(pari jure)</hi> coagulable in Spirit of Urine, (exquiſitely deflegmed) which being then reduced to a more fixt <hi>Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack,</hi> if not by it ſelf, yet by ſubliming (together) with that which is the product of humane Urine, becomes one (homogeneally) with it, and whatever (with it) abides the teſt of ſublimation, in that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50996:39"/>more fixed bodily form, is ever after univocally, homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneally, and identically the ſame, hath the ſame <hi>Lunar Blas,</hi> and being reviv'd with an (Alcaly, or otherwiſe) gives the ſame coagulating Spirit, which will coagulate Spirit of Wine. Behold here the admirable nature of the Spirit of Mans Urine, how it plays its part among all other Concretes, Spirits, Acetous, Oleagenous, Vinous, Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizate, and Urinous; As <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> Rod did with the Rods of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Inchanters, it devoured them all, either aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulating them to it ſelf in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50996:40"/>matter and form, or deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reducing them (at laſt) to mere inſipid Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Water. Here you have a body at laſt of an admirable product (not Vulgar but Philoſophical <hi>Sal Armoniack</hi>) concerning which, I have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much yet to write, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, my writings will be more knotty then <hi>Apollo's</hi> Oracles, till you learn to diſtinguiſh between <hi>Sal Armoniack</hi> Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Philoſophical.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:50996:40"/>
            <head>The unheard of Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roclyte Doctrin of <hi>Sal Armoniack,</hi> both <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical.</head>
            <p>IN my Pyrotechny Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Illuſtrated, which contains the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and Third part, accounting my vindication of <hi>Helmont,</hi> and Explication of Nature for the firſt part, being originally in Latine wrote to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50996:41"/>and making with my other Writings but one Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, I writing of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Liquor, or Fire, did paraphraſtically interpret that place of <hi>Helmont. Ars inda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gando ſollicita eſt Corpori, quod tantae puritatis Symphonia col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luderet nobiſcum, ut a corrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente nequirent diſſipaeri, ac tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſtupefacta eſt Religio, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perta latice,</hi> &amp;c. To which place, I ſhall remit the Reader, for what is there ſpoken too, not intending here a repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but a further illuſtration of things more briefly or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely diſcourſed of there. I obſerved it to be a Body,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50996:41"/>which Art was ſo inquiſitively ſollicitous to find, but ſuch a one, as might play with us or make us ſport <hi>(colluderet)</hi> by its harmony of ſo great purity, as not to be capable of diſſipation, by means of any corruptive agent or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſuch play or ſport is more pleaſant to a true Artiſt, then the Lords of the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> could have expected from <hi>Sampſon,</hi> yet this pulls down, and deſtroys as he did, (not Houſes) but the moſt ſolid compact bodies; and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion like maintains its ground, although very few Gallants and Ladies have that happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50996:42"/>to ſee the prizes plaid by this Anomalous Combatant. This body I there forbore to diſcover, except myſtically and parabolically; but here I ſhall plainly enough, to a Son of Art, diſcover the ſame, It is as I ſaid, a Body of a Spiritual indeſtructible Salt, in plain terms, it is the Salt of Humane Urine, or <hi>Sal Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack,</hi> not Vulgar (the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Urine, Soot, and Sea-Salt) but Philoſophical, to which the Vulgar is related, as ☿ Vulgar, is to the ☿ of the Philoſophers. The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion now will be how this <hi>Sal Armoniack</hi> Philoſophical
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50996:42"/>is made, which I think I have ſufficiently declared to a Son of Art; but I ſhall be a little more plainer and candid in my diſcovery, That moſt acute ſubtile penetrative Spirit of Mans Urine, by the help of another <hi>medium,</hi> not of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ferment from it ſelf, but centrally one I ſay with it, muſt be united to an <hi>Acidum,</hi> not Corroſive, <hi>ſed naturae ſuae gratiſſimum.</hi> This <hi>Acidum</hi> muſt be equally volatile with the Salt of Urine, before it can be Married or United in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately with it. Then by often Circulations it attains that height of purity to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50996:43"/>
               <hi>Ens ſalium, ſummum ſalium &amp; faliciſſimum.</hi> After all this, I muſt conclude with that ſaying of the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Helmont</hi> in another caſe, <hi>Chap. de Feb.</hi> ſpeaking there concerning the <hi>Aurum Horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale, Tametſi paucis abſolvi ſecretum quod medicum nobilitat iſtudque paraſſe pro primo vice ingentis operis eſt pendetque directio a manu ejus qui dator eſt omnium donorum bonorum.</hi> So I may well ſay in this, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I have diſcover'd the matter more plainly then any other, yet when attained, the way of working with it, is not eaſie, but depends from
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50996:43"/>his teaching who is the giver of every perfect gift; to whoſe Tutoridge I leave the honeſt inquirer and ſearcher after Truth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Carbones emunt atque vitra,</l>
               <l>Dii vero ſuderibus vendunt Artes.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. r. in the Microcoſme, p. 9. r. Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureous, <hi>idem</hi> p. 10. p. 17. for Urine r: Wine, <hi>idem</hi> for Aetherical r. Aetherial, p. 19. for even r. sver, p. 20. for the r. he, p. 32. for ſaeks r. ſeeks, p. 39. for ſublimary r. ſublunary, p. 43. for Alcalid r. Alcaly.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
